A Guide to the Papers of K. Edward Lay
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of K. Edward Lay
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
viu03696
This collection is 30 cu. ft. (ca.)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was a gift from K. Edward Lay, 104 Wilson Court, Charlottesville, Va. on 16 May 2000.
Biographical/Historical Information
Cary D. Langhorne Professor of Architcture, University of Virginia.
Scope and Content Information
Papers of K. Edward Lay consist of documentation of buildings and houses in Charlottesville and Albemarle County, Virginia, many of which are included in his book The architecture of Jefferson country and includes photographs, slides, measured drawings, copies of historical documents and correspondence.
The collection also contains historical information on Jefferson's master builders at the University of Virginia, the history of the University of Virginia School of Architecture, and architects who worked in Charlottesville and Albemarle County, Virginia.
Contents List
- Dwellings-Albemarle County and Charlottesville
  - Abell-Gleason House, (Robert L. Vickery Home), Charlottesville, 1859 1974-1995 (Box 1)
  - Ackley, (Martha Jefferson House; Allen Wheat House), Charlottesville, 1920-1921 1956 (Box 1)
  - Airslie, Keswick, early 20th century, 1990 1990-1995 (Box 1)
  - Albemarle House, Blenheim, 1983, 1987 1991-1995 (Box 1)
  - Alberene Soapstone Company Houses, (James H. Serene property), Alberene, 1893-1899 1978-1996 (Box 1)
  - Alderman House, (Mrs. Edwin A. Alderman Home), Charlottesville, 1932 1981 (Box 1)
  - Allen Dale, (Ridgeview tenant house; J. Coleman Home; Norwood Shores Tenant Home), Albemarle, 19th century 1994 (Box 1)
  - Alluvia, Advance Mills, ca. 1936 1995 (Box 1)
  - Allwood House, Crozet, ca. 1840 1995 (Box 1)
  - Ammonett Farm, Albemarle, ca. 1878, 1980 1980 (Box 1)
  - Anchorage, Albemarle, 1909, 1961 1977 (Box 1)
  - Anchorage, (White Family Home; Charles Lewis Home), Red Hill, ca. 1830 1977-1994 (Box 1)
  - Annex, Keswick, 20th century n.d. (Box 1)
  - Arcadia, (Clifton Waller Barrett Home), Farmington, 1960-1963 1989-1990 (Box 1)
  - Ardwood, Earlysville 1962 (Box 1)
  - Arrowhead 1, (Charles E. Meriwether Home; Governor Thomas Gilmer, owner), Red Hill, ca. 1828; Arrowhead 2, Red Hill, (Hard Acre; Office Hill; Reverend Edgar Woods Home), 1850s-1870s 1974-1995 (Box 1)
  - Arrows, Crossroads, North Garden n.d. (Box 1)
  - Ash Lawn-Highland, (Highlands; Upper Plantation; owners - James Monroe, John E. Massey, Jay Winston Johns, College of William and Mary), ca. 1799, ca. 1867 1973-1998 (Box 1)
  - Auburn Hill, (John Edward Timberlake House), Simeon, ca. 1842-1845 1990-1995 (Box 1)
  - Augmar Farm, Buck Island, 19th century 1987-1995 (Box 1)
  - "A" General 1979-1989 (Box 1)
    Abell-Garnett House, ca. 1860-1880; Acorn Cottage, 19th century, ca. 1951; Acorn Hill Farm; Adventure Farm, 20th century; Alicent, 20th century; Allen (Orville) House, ca. 1870; Alluvial Bottoms, ca. 1806; Alta Vista (Robert Fray Farm), ca. 1904; Altevogt House, 1924; American Four Square, early 20th century; Ampthill, 1732; Anchorage, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, 19th century; Antrim Duplex, 1889; Antrim House (Charlottesville), 1884-1887; Antrim House (Mt. Fair); Apperson Boswell House, ca. 1830; Argyll (The Lodge); Argyll, 20th century (?); Arrowhead (Robert E. Shaw House), ca. 1893; Ashton, ca. 1860; Azalea (James Francis Fry), ca. 1839
  - Bachelors Hall, (Blue Fok Farm), Browns Cove, 18th century 1974 (Box 1)
  - Bachelors Quarters, (Deer View; New Hadden; Page Home; Peter Taylor Home; Was School), early 19th century, 1980s 1984-1995 (Box 1)
  - Ballard-Abell Farm, Crozet, ante 1850, ca. 1865-1885 1981 (Box 1)
  - Barclay House, (Thomas Staples Home; Dr. James Barclay Home), Scottsville, ca. 1825 1939-1995 (Box 1)
  - Barksdale-Day Farm, Piney Mountain, Albarene, ca. 1894, mid 19th century 1981 (Box 1)
  - Barracks (Revolutionary War Prisoner Camp; Garland Garth Home; 1977 (Box 1)
  - Barrackside; George Carr Home; William S. P. Mayo Home), Albemarle, ca. 1819, 1930-1931
  - Barringer Mansion, (Dr. Paul Barringer Home), Charlottesville, 1896, 1985 n.d. (Box 1)
  - Barrsden, (Dr. D. Minor Home; Holladay Home; James Barr Home), Eastham, ca. 1820, 1930s 1978-1990 (Box 1)
  - Batna, Free Union, 1855 1976 (Box 1)
  - Beau Pre, (Frank Warren Home), Charlottesville, 20th century n.d. (Box 1)
  - Beaver Dam Farm, (Estes), Earlysville, ca. 1898 n.d. (Box 1)
  - Bel Aire, (James Michie Home; D. J. Augustus Michie Home), Advance Mills, ca. 1825 1980-1989 (Box 1)
  - Bellair, (Reverend Charles Wingfield, Jr. Home; Martin Dawson Home; Reverend Walker Timberlake Home), Carters Bridge, 1794 1974-1992 (Box 2)
  - Bellair Houses (subdivision), Albemarle, mid 20th century 1983 (Box 2)
  - Belle Grove, (Daniel Scott Home; Valmont; site of 1st Courthouse; Nathaniel Anderson, Jr. Home; John W. Gantt Home), Scottsville, 1745, ca. 1800, ca. 1975, ca. 1979 1977-1999 (Box 2)
  - Belle Haven, (J. L. Pitts Home), Scottsville, ca. 1880 1990-1996 (Box 2)
  - Belmont, Browns Cove, mid 18th century 1995 (Box 2)
  - Belmont, (John Manoah Carr Home; Bell-Mont; Slaughter W. Ficklin Home), Charlottesville, 1790s, 1813, ca. 1840 1959-1998 (Box 2)
  - Belmont 2, (Charles D. Everett Home), Keswick, 1858 1991 (Box 2)
  - Belmont 3, Keswick, ca. 1883 n.d. (Box 2)
  - Belmont 4, (Alfred Braun Home; Giant filmed here), Keswick, late 19th century, 1950s 1978-1995 (Box 2)
  - Belvoir, (patterned after Gunston Hall), Charlottesville, ca. 1928 1975-1995 (Box 2)
  - Belvoir Farm, Keswick Hunt, 1974 1985-1994 (Box 2)
  - Belvoir 2, (Hugh Nelson Home), Cismont, 1790, burned 1836, 1974 1978-1995 (Box 2)
  - Belvoir 3, Cismont, 19th century 1996 (Box 2)
  - Ben-Coolyn, (Major James Clark Home; Lewellyn Pugh Home; 1995 (Box 2)
  - Fruitland; Tall Oaks; Bogert Home; Pines moved to Cistmont), Keswick, early 19th century, ca. 1914
  - Bentivar, (Garland Carr Home), Eastham, Albemarle, ca. 1825 1970-1996 (Box 2)
  - Bibb-Wolfe House, (John H. Bibb Home; Walter Everett Fowler, owner; Ezra M. Wolfe Home), Charlottesville, ca. 1845 1995 (Box 2)
  - Bird Haven, (Brown Family Home), Greenwood, early 19th century 1989-1995 (Box 2)
  - Birdwood, (WilliamGarth Home; Hore Browse Trist Home; Hollis Rinehart Home; Woods Garth Home), Charlottesville, 1819 1979-1997 (Box 2)
  - Bishop House, (Joseph Bishop Home), Vinegar Hill, 1803 1993 (Box 2)
  - Bishop House, Woodridge, ca. 1800 1976-1995 (Box 2)
  - Blaetterman House, Charlottesville, early 19th century 1991 (Box 2)
  - Blair House, (William Adams Home; Omohundro Home; Tipton Home), Scottsville, ca. 1844 1978-1999 (Box 2)
  - Blair Park, (Mountain Plains site; Michael Woods House), Crozet, ca. 1920 n.d. (Box 2)
  - Bleak House, (Hawky Ferguson Home), Free Union, ca. 1830 n.d. (Box 2)
  - Bleak House, (Holly House), Free Union, ca. 1840, 1851, 1958 1975-1995 (Box 2)
  - Blenheim 1, (William and Edward Carter House), Blenheim, 18th century 1991 (Box 2)
  - Blenheim 2, (Andrew Stevenson Home), Blenheim, 1846, 1990 1977-1995 (Box 2)
  - Bloomfield, (Paul H. Goodloe Home; Bloomfield Academy; Rice Garland, owner; Charles Harper Home; J. Tatnall Lea Home), Ivy, 1849, ca. 1920 1976-1998 (Box 3)
  - Blue Ridge Farm, (William B. Smith Home; Alton Park; Glooston Manor; Gloucester Manor; Herman Danforth Newcomb Home; Shaw Home; Dr. Frederick Owsley Home; Purcell Home; James Durrett Home), Greenwood, mid 19th century 1978-1994 (Box 3)
  - Bonahora, (Benjamin Collins Flannagan Home; Judge Thomas Barton Lyons Home; A. G. Carter Home), Charlottesville, 1858 1969-1995 (Box 3)
  - Bond House, Belmont, Charlottesville, 1912 1994-1996 (Box 3)
  - Boxwood, (W. A. Rinehart Home; Institute of Textile Technology), Albemarle, 20th century 1995-1998 (Box 3)
  - Boxwood, Farmington, 1940 1993 (Box 3)
  - Boxwood Lane Farm, (R. A. H. Foster Home; Boxwood Lawn Farm), Batesville, 1860, ca. 1903 1985-1997 (Box 3)
  - Braeburn, Free Union, burned Civil War, ca. 1870 1983-1992 (Box 3)
  - Braeview, (W. Allen Perkins Home), Charlottesville, 1923, ca. 1928 1981 (Box 3)
  - Branchlands, Albemarle, 20th century 1982-1995 (Box 3)
  - Branch Point, (Landfall; Clifton Brown Home), Browns Cove, ca. 1770, ca. 1825, burned ca. 1940 1995 (Box 3)
  - Brand-Hartman House, Charlottesville, 1893 1978-1995 (Box 3)
  - Brechin House, Charlottesville, ca. 1872 n.d. (Box 3)
  - Breezeway, Albemarle, 20th century n.d. (Box 3)
  - Breezy Oaks, (Albert Johnson Home; freed black house), Cismont, ca. 1885 1978 (Box 3)
  - Bremen, Mount Fair, ca. 1900 1988 (Box 3)
  - Briar Creek Farm, (Sears-Roebuck), Albemarle, late 19th century 1993 (Box 3)
  - Bridle Spur Farm, (Clarksville Tavern; Sunny Side; William B. Pace Home), Clarksville, 18th century, 19th century, razed 1937, 1937-1938 1995 (Box 3)
  - Brightberry (Captain Brightberry Brown Home; Headquarters; Nimrod Brown Home), Browns Cove, 1818, mid 19th century, late 19th century 1949-1995 (Box 3)
  - Broad Oak, (John Rodgers House; Edward C. Mead Home), Keswick, late 18th century, ca. 1840, 1874 n.d. (Box 3)
  - Brock House, University Circle, 1910 1995 (Box 3)
  - Brockenbrough House, (Turkey Run Farm; Holly Hill; Dawson House; Thomas W. Brockenbrough Home; Mary Cunningham Home), Albemarle, 18th century 1991-1996 (Box 3)
  - Broken Creek Farm, Albemarle, ca. 1917, 1978 1995 (Box 3)
  - Brookhaven, Farmington, 1941 n.d. (Box 3)
  - Brook Hill, (Dunkum House; Burke Home), Albemarle, ca. 1820 1979-1995 (Box 3)
  - Brook Hill, (James Minor Home; Nelson Barksdale Home), Charlottesville, ca. 1815 1992-1995 (Box 3)
  - Brooks Farm, Albemarle, ca. 1800 1996 (Box 3)
  - Brookwood, (Hunter Perry House), Albemarle, 1900, 1975 1984 (Box 3)
  - Broomfield, Scottsville 1990 (Box 3)
  - Broomley, (Dr. Stephen H. Watts House), Farmington, 1930-1931 1984 (Box 3)
  - Brown-Parrot House, (John Brown, Jr. Home; Garland Brown Home), Crozet, ca. 1780, 1977 razed 1976-1997 (Box 3)
  - Bryan-Stallings House, Charlottesville, 1900 1998 (Box 3)
  - Buck Island 2, (John R. Campbell Home; Buckeyeland; John C. Wood Home; B. C. Flanagan Home; Charles Lilburn Lewis Home; George Christopher Gilmer Home), ca. 1810 1991 (Box 3)
  - Buena Vista (George Rogers Clark's birthplace site), Albemarle, ca. 1734, 1862 1978-1995 (Box 3)
  - Bundoran Farm, Covesville, ca. 1830-1850 1991 (Box 3)
  - Burress Farms, (Old Homestead), Free Union, ca. 1850, late 18th century 1999 (Box 3)
  - Butler-Norris House, (Edward Butler House; Opie Norris, owner), Charlottesville, ca. 1808 1978-1993 (Box 3)
  - "Ba-Bl" General 1958-2000 (Box 3)
    Baber House, Batesville, early 20th century; Henry Bailey House, Charlottesville, ca. 1911; T. W. Bailey House, Charlottesville, ca. 1907; Ballard House, Crozet, ca. 1830; R. M. Balthis House, Charlottesville, 1900; Bancroft, Charlottesville, 20th century; Bargaman House, Crozet, ca. 1906; Barkley-Sherman House, Charlottesville, ca. 1949; Barksdale House, Staunton, ca. 1875; Barksdale House, Charlottesville, mid 19th century; Barrack Grove, Albemarle, early 19th century; Barterbrook Manor, Charlottesville; Batesville House (VSH 692), 1890; Baughman House (VSH 715); Beacon Hill House, Earlysville, ca. 1875
    Beauchamps, Monticello Mountain, 1940s; Beaulieu, Albemarle; Beau Val (Cobham); Beaver Creek Farm, Keswick-Cismont, early 19th century; Beck House, Turkeysag Gap, 18th century; Bellafield Farm, Keswick, 20th century; Bell House, Charlottesville, ca. 1775; Belle Oak, Albemarle; Belmont, Shadwell, mid 18th century; Belton Farms, Albemarle, mid 20th century; Belvedere, Albemarle; Belvidere, Albemarle; Benwood (Glenallen), ca. 1860-1880; Berry Hill, Albemarle, 1816; Berry Hill, Halifax County, 1842-1844; Betsy Belle, Albemarle
    Bibb House, Albemarle, late 19th century, 1920s; Bingler House (Cherry Avenue), Charlottesville, 1915; Bingler House (King Street), Charlottesville, 1939; Bingler House (King Street), Charlottesville, 1939; Birdsong, Free Union, 1990; Black Angus Farm, Albemarle, ca. 1800; a Black Family House (Holsinger); Blake Farm, Woodridge, ca. 1825, late 19th century; Blandfield, Essex County, ca. 1771; Bleak Hill, Scottsville, ca. 1760; Blue Cedar, Shadwell, ca. 1939-1941; Blue Cottage, (dependency building for a University of Virginia dormitory), 14th & 15 Streets, ca. 1838; Blue Grass Valley Farm, Albemarle; Blue Ridge Farm, Free Union, 19th century; 1932 Blue Ridge Road Home, Meadowbrook Hills
  - "Bo-Bu" General 1959-1995 (Box 3)
    Bohn (Rufus) House, Appleberry Mountain, 18th century; Boone-White House, Charlottesville, 1914-1915, 1932; Boxwood Ridge, Ivy, ca. 1866-1873; Braedalbane, Farmington, 20th century; Briar Patch, Bellair, 1957; Brechin-Smith House, Charlottesville, 1881; Breeding-Wood Log House, Earlysville, 1830-1840; Brightberry, Crozet, 18th century, 1800-1820; Bridlepath Drive House, Boar's Head; Brinnington Farm, 20th century; Brondsema House, Crozet, 1940; Brook Cottage, Albemarle, ca. 1930; Brookley, Scottsville; Brooks House (Albert Brooks, free black), Charlottesville, 1870, 1925; Brookside, Campbell, 20th century; Brookside Cottage, Ivy, ca. 1920; Broomhollow, Albemarle, ca. 1800; Brown House, Charlottesville, 1879-1881; Brown House, North Garden, ca. 1800; Bruce House, Boonesville, late 19th century - early 20th century; Bruce House, Earlysville, ca. 1870
    Buck Island (John H. Wood), Albemarle, 18th century; Buck Island 1(Randolph Lewis), Albemarle, 1799; Buck Island Creek, Albemarle; Buck's Elbow Mountain, 19th century; Buena Vista, King George County, 1923; Buffalo Run Farm, Advance Mills; Bungalow/Bungalow Style, Cismont, ca. 1920/early 20th century; Burgess-Hawkins House, Charlottesville, 1888, 1911; 1702 Burnley Avenue, Charlottesville, ca. 1918; Burnley (Frank) House, Charlottesville, 1923; Bushnell-Wilkinson Carriage House, Charlottesville, ca. 1880s or 1910, 1927, 1965
  - Canaan Farm, Warren, 1785 1965-2000 (Box 4)
  - Carlton, Albemarle 1956-1995 (Box 4)
  - Carr House, The Meadows, ca. 1830, razed 1980s 1995 (Box 4)
  - Carr House, (Cream Street), Charlottesville, ca. 1830, ca. 1850, ca. 1930, razed 1975 1975 (Box 4)
  - Carrs Hill, University of Virginia, ante 1860, 1870-1871, 1907-1909 1993-1995 (Box 4)
  - Carrsbrook, (Peter Carr House), Charlottesville, 1780s or 1794 1939-1998 (Box 4)
  - Carrsgrove 1, Charlottesville, 1747 1992 (Box 4)
  - Carrsgrove 2, Charlottesville, 1892, burned 1978 1978-1995 (Box 4)
  - Carter-Gilmer House, Charlottesville, 1820s, late 19th century, 1955, 1988 1980-1995 (Box 4)
  - Carver House (High Street), Charlottesville, 1886-1889, 1994 1993-1995 (Box 4)
  - Casa Maria, Greenwood, 1919-1922, 1928 1991-1993 (Box 4)
  - Castalia 1, (Claim House), Cismont, 1747 1992 (Box 4)
  - Castalia 2, (Murry Boocock Home), Cismont, 1850, 1899, 1987 1984-1995 (Box 4)
  - Castlebrook, Batesville, ca. 1835, 1905 1992 (Box 4)
  - Castle Hill, Cismont-Cobham, 1764, 1824, 1844, 1947, 1991 1978-1999 (Box 4)
  - Castlewood, Yancey Mills, 1790 1986-1991 (Box 4)
  - Catterton House, Free Union, ca. 1835, 1989 1976-1988 (Box 4)
  - Cedar Grove, Blenheim, 1798, 1820s, 1960s 1980-1992 (Box 4)
  - Cedars, The, (The Casino, The Dower), Yancy Mills, ca. 1855 1976-1992 (Box 4)
  - Cherry Hill, Ivy, 20th century 1991-1995 (Box 5)
  - Cherry Valley, (Jesse Garth House), Albemarle, 1805, 1820s, late 19th century 1997-1999 (Box 5)
  - Chester, ca. 1847-1891 1982-1995 (Box 5)
  - Chestnut Avenue Plantation, Earlysville, 18th century 1958-1996 (Box 5)
  - Chiswell, Greenwood, early 20th century n.d. (Box 5)
  - Christmas Hill, Esmont, ca. 1850 1979-1980 (Box 5)
  - Church Hill, (John Schuyler Moon Summer Home), Keene, ca. 1830 1991 (Box 5)
  - Church Hill, (John Toole House), Crossroads, ca. 1847, ca. 1860 1989 (Box 5)
  - Cinnamon Hill, Cobham, ca. 1918 n.d. (Box 5)
  - Cismont Manor, Keswick-Cismont, 1836, 1847, razed 1894 1979 (Box 5)
  - Clermont, Charlottesville, ante 1860, ca. 1917, burned 1922 1990 (Box 5)
  - Cliffside, (Virginia Moore Home), Scottsville, 1810?, 1835, ca. 1855 1977-2000 (Box 5)
  - Clifton, Greenwood, ca. 1875, 1986 1993-1995 (Box 5)
  - Clifton (Thomas Mann Randolph), North Milton, Albemarle, ca. 1800, 1820s, 1940 1982-1995 (Box 5)
  - Clover Fields 1, (Nicholas Meriwether), Cismont, ca. 1765, razed 1846 1992 (Box 5)
  - Clover Fields 2, Cismont, 1846 1973-1998 (Box 5)
  - Clover Hill, (Burnley), Albemarle, late 18th century, mid 19th century 1989-1992 (Box 5)
  - Clover Hill, (Thomas Walker Meriwether House), Cismont, ca. 1830 1992-1998 (Box 5)
  - Clunie, Earlysville, ca. 1870 1976 (Box 5)
  - Cobham Park, (William Cabell Rives, Jr.), Cobham, ca. 1856 1995-2000 (Box 5)
  - Cole House, Charlottesville, 1934-1935 n.d. (Box 5)
  - Coleswood, Green Mountain, ca. 1902 1980-1993 (Box 5)
  - Colle, (General Riedesel Home), Simeon, ca. 1774, razed 1933 1973-1976 (Box 5)
  - Colonial Cottage, (Fore House), Scottsville, ca. 1780 1978-1995 (Box 5)
  - Comyn Hall, (McCue House), Charlottesville, ca. 1900 1979-1993 (Box 5)
  - Conway-Gilmer House, Charlottesville, ca. 1874 n.d. (Box 5)
  - Copley (Massie House) n.d. (Box 5)
  - Creel House, Advance Mills, ca. 1815, ca. 1840 n.d. (Box 5)
  - Creoch, Farmington, Charlottesville, 20th century 1979 (Box 5)
  - Crestwood, Albemarle, ca. 1890-1900 1976-1995 (Box 5)
  - Crutchfield, Albemarle, late 18th century 1991 (Box 5)
  - "C" General 1955-1995 (Box 6)
    : Caledonia, Piedmont Hunt Country, 1812; Campbell Station Farm, Keswick Hunt; Carey House, Charlottesville, 1887 and ca. 1890s; Carr Place (Strange Place), Albemarle County, 1800; Carr (Dabney) House, Israel's Mountain; Carr (Hugh F.) House, Albemarle, late 19th century; Carr-Crawford House, Batesville, ca. 1910; Carroll (J. Payne) Home, Charlottesville, ca. 1909; Carrollton Manor, Charlottesville, ca. 1909-1910; Carrsbrook, Albemarle County, 20th century; Carter House, Samuel Miller district; Carter-Short House, Charlottesville, 1930; Carver House (Park Street), Charlottesville, 1908; Carver House (West High Street), Charlottesville, 1891; Carver-Blakey House, Charlottesville, 1894; Carver-Fitzhugh House, Charlottesville, 1900; Carver-Townsend House, Charlottesville, 1894; Casita, Albemarle County, 1870s-1880s; Catholic Diocese House, Earlysville, ca. 1825; Cave (E. L.) House, Charlottesville, 1912; Cave-Musselman House, Charlottesville, 1923
    Cedar Shakes, Keswick Hunt, 20th century; Cedarmere, Boonesville, ca. 1850; Cedar Valley Farm, Albemalre, ca. 1800; Chaddick House, Charlottesville, 1910; Chancellor-Cocke House (University Avenue), Charlottesville, early 20th century; Chapman House, Charlottesville, 1920; Chardon, Farmington, 20th century; Cherokee, Keswick Hunt, 20th century; Chimney Corner; Keswick, 20th century; Chisholm House, Charlottesville, 1936; Christiana, Farmington, 20th century; Clancy House, Charlottesville, 1925; Clarke Manor, Albemarle, 1794; Clarkston-Tonsler House, Charlottesville, 1915; Clements House (Allen-Clements House), Charlottesville, 1896; Cole (James) House, Charlottesville, 1870-1875
    Coles Tavern, Charlottesville, early 19th century; Colthurst Farm, Albemarle, 1965; Colvin-Tilman House, Charlottesville, 1893; Comer (Samuel) House, Charlottesville; Conduff House, Charlottesville, ca. 1941; Coniston, Piedmont, ca. 1850; Connell-Neve House, Charlottesville, ca. 1894; Cool Stream Farm (Ephrain Seamonds House), Free Union, 1812; Coombs-Paxson Cottage (Swiss Village), Charlottesville, 1924-1925; Coty House, Ednam Village, 20th century; Cox House (Carolyn Cox Home), Charlottesville, 20th century; Crofton Hill, Albemarle, 20th century; Crouse (William H.) House, Farmington, 20th century; Crozet House, Crozet, 1890; Curdland (William A. Curd), Batesville, ca. 1932
  - Darby's Folly (Chestnut Ridge, Old Waddell Place, J. Woods Garth, Sr. Home), Farmington, ca. 1750-1760, ca. 1810, 1938 n.d. (Box 6)
  - Dargavel n.d. (Box 6)
  - Deepdene, Albemarle, 1892 1980-1990 (Box 6)
  - Deer Lodge n.d. (Box 6)
  - Dinsmore-Dabney-Harmon House, (Pleasant View, Judge A. D. Dabney Home, John P. Harmon Home, Richard Duke Home, Garland Home), Charlottesville, early 19th century 1990-1993 (Box 6)
  - Doll House, (Thacker House), Scottsville, ca. 1810 1978-1995 (Box 6)
  - Donegal 1, (Oakland), Warren, Albemarle, ca. 1804-1806, garden 1841 1985-1995 (Box 6)
  - Donegal 2, (Oakland, Oak Ridge), Warren, Albemarle 1888, 1926, burned 1926, ca. 1961 1991-1996 (Box 6)
  - Dovedale, (Zachariah Shackelford House), Stony Point, 1806-1815 1977-1990 (Box 6)
  - Drover's Rest, Scottsville Turnpike Road, 1890-1910 1991 (Box 6)
  - Duck-In Farm, Scottsville 1995 (Box 6)
  - Duke House, Charlottesville, 1884, 1987 1995 (Box 6)
  - Dulaney House, Charlottesville, 1929 1995 (Box 6)
  - Dunkum-Dice House, (Dr. Diggs House, Fire Station), Charlottesville, 1843, razed 1965 1990-1995 (Box 6)
  - Dunkum-Spooner-Brown House, Charlottesville, 1842, ca. 1895, razed 1994 1994-1999 (Box 6)
  - Dunlora 1, (Claim House), Albemarle, 1760 1992 (Box 6)
  - Dunlora 2, (John Barclay Moon Home, Dabney Carr Home), Albemarle, burned 1828, 1840, burned 1916 1985-1995 (Box 6)
  - Dunlora 3, Albemarle, ca. 1916 1967-1998 (Box 6)
  - Dunn House, (Gibson Home, Little Owl Farm), Nortonsville, ca. 1825, 1991 n.d. (Box 6)
  - Durrett House, Esmont, 1905 1993-1994 (Box 6)
  - Dyer House, (Eugene Davis Home, Mantel in Carrsgrove), Charlottesville, ca. 1820, razed 1954-1992 (Box 6)
  - "D" General 1979-1995 (Box 6)
    Dabney House, Charlottesville, ca. 1870; Dabney-Thompson House, Charlottesville, 1894; Dargavel, Cismont, 1900, 1944; Davis House, Charlottesville, 1825, razed; Crenshaw (John) Farm (Dead Oak Farm), Earlysville, mid 19th century, 1870; Dean House, Free Union, late 19th century; Deep Acres, Farmington Hunt, 1948; Deerlodge, Keswick, 1850, 1970; Deer Run, Ednam Forest, 1969; Devon Road House, Ednam Forest, 20th century; Devonhurst, Keswick Hunt, 20th century; Disney-Keith House, Charlottesville, 1884
    Doswell House (Old Taylor House), Albemarle, ca. 1826; Douglas Avenue House, Charlottesville, early 20th century; Dowell (John) House, Albemarle; Dowell (Madison) House, Albemarle, ca. 1800; Dowell Tenant House, Mt. Chapel Community, ca. 1836; Ducharme, North Garden, 1920; Dudley (M. A.) House, Charlottesville, ca. 1925; Dudley Mountain Road House, Albemarle, early 20th century; Duff (E. L.) House, Ednam Forest, 1968; Duke House (R. W. Duke House), Charlottesville, late 19th century, razed; Dunn House, Free Union, late 19th century; Dunn (Dr. Thomas Martin), Free Union, late 19th century-early 20th century; Dutch Colonial, Charlottesville, early 20th century
  - East Belmont, Keswick, ca. 1811, 1825 1978-1994 (Box 6)
  - Echol's Bungalow, Charlottesville, 1895-1896 1996 (Box 6)
  - Edgehill, Shadwell, 1790, 1828, interior burned 1916, 1961 1976-1998 (Box 6)
  - Edgemont, (James Powell Cocke Home, Graham Clark Home, William Snead Home), South Garden, 1795, 1936 1950-1998 (Box 6)
  - Edgewood, Cashs Corner, 1911, 1957, 1968 1975-1995 (Box 7)
  - Edgeworth, Cashs Corner, 18th century, burned 1835, 1837, 1859,1933 1983-1995 (Box 7)
  - Edgmont, (Christopher Clark, John Gilmer Home), Eastham, 1780, 1827, 1951 1978-1999 (Box 7)
  - Ednam, (John L. Dryden Home), Farmington vicinity, ca. 1901, ca. 1937 1979-1994 (Box 7)
  - Edwards House, (Bluford Brockman Home), Burnley, ca. 1780 or 1812 1989 (Box 7)
  - Eldon Farm, (C. H. Page Home), Cobham, ca. 1925 n.d. (Box 7)
  - Elk Run Farm, Free Union, ca. 1884 1976 (Box 7)
  - Ellerslie, (Three Rivers, 1976), Albemarle, 1842 1977-1995 (Box 7)
  - Enderly, (Richard K. Flannagan Home), Charlottesville, 1859-1860, 1921 n.d. (Box 7)
  - Enniscorthy Cabin, (Cabin in the Grove), Green Mountain, 18th century, razed 1984 (Box 7)